Guide to the Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers, 1880, 1919-1998 and undated RL.10086
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Abraham Joshua Heschel papers
1880, 1919-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Heschel, Abraham Joshua
RL.10086
162 Linear Feet 319 boxes
אברהם יהושע השל היה מלומד והוגה דעות בעל שם בינלאומי, תיאולוג ופעיל חברתי ופוליטי. השל נולד בוורשה, פולין, נצר למשפחת רבנים חסידיים מיוחסת ולמד פילוסופיה בברלין. הוא גורש מפרנקפורט והגיע לוורשה ומשם עקר ללונדון ערב הפלישה הגרמנית לפולין. לאחר שהות קצרה בלונדון היגר השל לארצות הברית. בתחילה לימד בבית המדרש לרבנים של התנועה הרפורמית בסינסנטי, ולאחר מכן עבר לסמינר היהודי התיאולוגי בניו יורק שם שימש כפרופסור לאתיקה ולקבלה עד מותו בשנת 1972. בנוסף להשתתפותו הפעילה בנושאים של צדק חברתי ובדיאלוג הבין-דתי, היה השל גם מלומד ומורה רוחני ותרם תרומה חשובה למדעי היהדות. כהוגה דעות של הדת היתה מטרתו של השל להגביר ולהעמיק את התובנות הרוחניות של היהדות ובמהלך חייו השפיע על דורות של יהודים ולא- יהודים. הארכיון האישי של אברהם יהושע השל מקיף את השנים 1880-1998 ומתעד את חייו האישיים, האקדמיים והציבוריים. הארכיון כולל תכתובות, כתבים של השל ועליו, כתבי יד מודפסים, קטעי עיתונות, כתבים שיצאו לאור ומעט תמונות וחפצי קודש. האוסף מספק תובנות לזהותו של השל כמנהיג רוחני ומסביר כיצד היה מעמדו זה קשור בקשר עמוק לחייו האישיים והמקצועיים. האוסף מחולק לפי הנושאים הבאים: חומר מוקלט, התכתבויות, חומר אישי ומשפחתי, פעילות ציבורית, חומר מוגבל וכתבים.
Abraham Joshua Heschel was an internationally known scholar, author, activist, and theologian. He was born in Warsaw, Poland into a distinguished family of Hasidic rebbes, and studied philosophy in Berlin, Germany. In 1938 he was deported from Frankfurt to Warsaw where he escaped to London just before the Nazi invasion. After a brief time in London he immigrated to the United States, first teaching at the Hebrew Union College and then at the Jewish Theological Seminary of America where he taught as Professor of Ethics and Mysticism until his death in 1972. In addition to his active participation in social justice issues and his interfaith work, Heschel was also a scholar and religious thinker who made significant contributions to Jewish studies. As a philosopher of religion, his goal was to make the spiritual insights of Judaism understandable and over the course of his lifetime influenced generations of Jews and non-Jews. The Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers span the years 1880 to 1998 and document Abraham Joshua Heschel's personal, academic, and public life. Items in this collection include correspondence, writings by and about Heschel, typescripts, clippings, printed material, and a small amount of photographs and artifacts. The materials in the collection provide insight to Heschel's identity as a spiritual leader and how this role was inextricably connected to his personal and professional life. The collection is organized into the following series: Audio, Correspondence, Personal and Family Materials, Public Activity, Restricted, and Writings.
Biographical Note
Abraham Joshua Heschel was an internationally known scholar, author, activist, and theologian. He was born in Warsaw, Poland into a distinguished family of Hasidic rebbes and was named after his great-grandfather, the Apter Rebbe, Avraham Yehoshua Heschel. His mother, Rivka Reizl, descended from the famed Rabbi Levi Yitzak of Berdichev and his father, Mosche Mordecai of Pelzovizna. Heschel studied philosophy in Berlin, Germany and was deported from Frankfurt to Warsaw where he escaped to London just before the Nazi invasion. After a brief time in London, he immigrated to the United States, first teaching at the Hebrew Union College and then at the Jewish Theological Seminary of America where he taught as Professor of Ethics and Mysticism until his death in 1972.
In addition to his active participation in social justice issues including civil rights and the plight of the Jews in the Soviet Union, and his interfaith work, Heschel was also a scholar and religious thinker who made significant contributions to every field of Jewish studies. As a philosopher of religion, his goal was to make the spiritual insights of Judaism understandable and over the course of his lifetime influenced generations of Jews and non-Jews, leaving a lasting impression all over the world.
Chronology
1907 Jan 11 born in Warsaw, Poland into a distinguished family of Hasidic rebbes.
1916 Nov 16 father dies during influenza epidemic, leaving Heschel and his mother and siblings (4 sisters Esther, Gittel, Sarah and Devorah, 1 brother Jacob) impoverished.
1925 arrives in Vilna, Poland (formerly Lithuania) to study at the secular Real-Gymnasium.
1927 comes to Berlin, Germany and enters both the Reform rabbinical school (Hochschule für die Wissenschaft des Judentums) and the University of Berlin. Heschel also informally studies at the Hildesheimer, an Orthodox rabbinical seminary. By January, 1931 Heschel completes his required courses at the university with a specialization in philosophy and minors in art history and Semitic philology.
1932 serves as Instructor in Talmud at the Hochschule für die Wissenschaft des Judentums in Berlin.
1932-1933 completes doctoral dissertation, Das Prophetische Bewusstsein (The Prophetic Consciousness), but is unable to publish it in Germany due to the political and legal changes sweeping the country. The book is finally published in Poland in 1935 and Heschel is awarded his Ph.D. on December 11, 1935.
1934 Jul completes his degree at the Hochschule.
1935 his first major work, Maimonides: Eine Biographie is published in German. The French edition is published in 1936 and the English edition in 1982.
1937-1938 becomes successor to Martin Buber as a teacher in the Frankfurt LehrHaus, an adult education center.
1938 Oct arrested and deported to Warsaw, Poland where he is later appointed to the chair of Jewish Philosophy by the Institute for Jewish Science.
1939 receives official confirmation from Julian Morgenstern, president of Hebrew Union College in Cincinnati, OH, of a position of a research fellow in Bible and Jewish Philosophy. Heschel leaves Warsaw for London, England to obtain an American visa for emigration to the United States. While in London, he founds the Institute for Jewish Learning.
1940 Mar leaves for the United States and arrives in New York City.
1940-1945 teaches at the Hebrew Union College (HUC) in Cincinnati, OH. He begins as a fellow of Jewish philosophy, is promoted to Instructor in Jewish Philosophy and Rabbinics in 1943 and to Associate Professor in 1944. While at HUC, he meets future wife Sylvia Straus, a concert pianist.
1945 The Earth is the Lord's: the Inner World of the Jew in Eastern Europe first presented, in shortened form, as a lecture in Yiddish that Heschel delivers to members of YIVO (Yiddish Scientific Institute) in New York City in January. During the same year is invited to teach at the Jewish Theological Seminary of America (JTS) in New York as Associate Professor of Jewish Ethics and Mysticism and becomes a naturalized citizen.
1946 Dec 10 marries Sylvia Straus in Los Angeles.
1950-1955 publishes 5 books, including The Earth is the Lord's: the Inner World of the Jew in Eastern Europe (1950), Man is not Alone (1951), The Sabbath (1951), Man's Quest for God (1954), God in Search of Man (1955).
1954 receives a Guggenheim Fellowship to "devote himself" to studies of the life and thought of Rabbi Yisroel ben Eliezer, known as Baal Shem Tov.
1960-1961 receives and accepts offers to be a visiting professor at two institutions, the University of Minnesota and the University of Iowa.
1961 Nov travels to Rome to meet with several Vatican officials as part of the upcoming Ecumenical Council. There Heschel meets Cardinal Bea for the first time. In 1962 Heschel writes the memorandum "On Improving Catholic-Jewish Relations" which becomes the foundational American Jewish Committee (AJC) contribution to the Vatican Declaration on the Jews.
1962 The Prophets and Torah min HaShamayim Volume I are published.
1963 Jan speaks at a conference on "Religion and Race" in Chicago, organized by the National Conference of Christians and Jews. Meets Martin Luther King Jr. for the first time.
1963 May delivers a series of three lectures at Stanford University which he revises and expands into Who is Man? The book is published in 1965 by Stanford University Press.
1965 participates in the Voting Rights March in Selma, Alabama. Heschel is also appointed by the Union Theological Seminary to serve as its Harry Emerson Fosdick Visiting Professor, the first Jewish scholar to be appointed to the faculty of the Protestant institution. His inaugural lecture is "No Religion is an Island." Torah min HaShamayim Volume II is published.
1964 Sep obtains a private audience with Pope Paul VI prior to the third session of the Ecumenical Council.
1966 Jan Notre Dame University confers upon Heschel its degree of Doctor of Laws, honoris causa.
1971 Mar obtains private audience with Pope Paul VI.
1971 receives honorary degree of Doctor of Hebrew Letters from Spertus College of Judaica in Chicago, Illinois.
1972 Dec 23 dies in New York City at the age of 65.
1973 Heschel's last books, Kotzk, a two-volume work in Yiddish, and A Passion for Truth are published. Torah min HaShamayim Volume III is published in 1990.
Collection Overview
The Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers span the years 1880 to 1998 and document Abraham Joshua Heschel's personal, academic, and public life, including his long-term involvement and leadership in social activism and other public activities, his reputation as a compelling and sought-after public speaker, and his far-reaching influence as a scholar and religious thinker. Items in this collection include correspondence, writings by and about Heschel, typescripts, clippings, printed material, and a small amount of photographs and artifacts. The materials in the collection provide insight to Heschel's identity as a spiritual leader and how this role was inextricably connected to his personal and professional life.
The collection is organized into the following series: Audio, Correspondence, Personal and Family Materials, Public Activity, Restricted, and Writings. Heschel maintained a meaningful, yet complex filing system. To balance preserving the original order with making the collection as accessible to researchers as possible, several key elements have been added to the collection guide:
•Scope note at the folder level. In many cases folder titles in the collection were reused, abbreviated, in Hebrew, or did not exist. Short descriptions of folder contents have been included not only to provide context for the materials, but also to make distinctions between the varying titles.
•Supplied/enhanced folder titles. In the case of missing or abbreviated titles, supplied titles (in brackets) were created. For folder titles written in Hebrew, the original folder title was documented along with its transliteration and English translation.
•Language extent. There are varying degrees in the amount of language materials in each folder and oftentimes multiple languages are represented in a single folder. To assist researchers, each folder description includes a note identifying the language(s) and their extent in the folder, with the dominant language listed first. The absence of a note indicates that all materials in the folder are in English. The following language categories are used: "A few" indicates that 1-25% of the materials are in another language(s); "Some" 26-65%; "Most" 66-99%; and "All" 100%.
Additionally there was a large of amount of clippings included in the Heschel collection which were generally in fragile condition. Where possible, these clippings were photocopied for preservation purposes and the originals discarded.
Provenance
The Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in May, 2012.
Access Restrictions
האוסף פתוח למחקר, אך קיימות הגבלות על חלקים מסוימים ממנו. ראה תיאור Restricted Series שבאוסף. חוקרים חייבים להרשם ולהסכים לחוקי ההגנה על זכויות יוצרים ועל פרטיות לפני השימוש באוסף. האוסף כולו או חלקים ממנו עשויים להיות שמורים מחוץ לספריה, במרכז השירות הספרייתי של אוניברסיטת דיוק. יתכן וידרשו עד 48 שעות על מנת להעביר את החומר ולאפשר שימוש מחקרי בו. חוקרים המעונינים להשתמש באוסף מתבקשים ליצור קשר עם צוות שירותי המחקר של ספרית דוד. מ. רובינשטיין לספרים נדירים ולכתבי יד, לפני ביקורם בספריה.
Collection is open for research. There are limits on the use of some parts of the collection; please see description below of 'Restricted Series'.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Related Materials
Photographs of Heschel participating in the Selma to Montgomery March (1965) can be found in the James Karales Photographs, Rubenstein Library, Duke University.
Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements; Vietnam War, 1961-1965 -- United States; Vatican Council (2nd: 1962-1965: Basilica di San Pietro in Vaticano); Torah; Talmud; Spiritual Life -- Judaism; Judaism; Judaism, Conservative; Judaism, Reconstructionist; Judaism, Reform; Religion -- Philosophy; Revelation -- Judaism; Sabbath; Social justice; Bible. Prophets; Civil rights; Hasidism; Holocaust; Israel; Jews, Soviet; Jewish philosophy -- 20th century; Jewish scholars; Judaism and politics; Judaism and social problems; Judaism -- Theology; Judaism -- United States -- Judaism and philosophy; Judaism -- Relations -- Catholic Church; Judaism -- Relations -- Christianity; Judaism -- Europe, Easter; Judaism -- Prayers and devotions; Rabbinical Literature; Religion; Palestine -- In Judaism; Philosophical Anthropology; Heschel, Sylvia Straus; Hebrew Union College; Jewish Theological Seminary of America
- Audio, circa 1960s; 1; 1 Box
  Scope and Contents note
  The Audio series contains one reel of a broadcast of an interview with Heschel on the radio show "Way to Go."
  - [Way to Go #227], 1
    - Original 1/4 inch open reel audio tape, circa 1960s (Box 307, Reel RL10086-RR-0001)
      Broadcast of radio show "Way to Go" with host Ormond Drake, Associate Dean, Division of General Education at New York University. Interviews Heschel primarily about Heschel's book God in Search of Man but also asks Heschel about himself. Heschel talks at length about key themes from the book including sense of wonder, enigma, and awe.
      Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room.
- Correspondence, 1923-1973; 2; 18 Boxes
  The Correspondence series primarily consists of letters classified as correspondence by Heschel. The correspondence is both personal and professional in nature and the topics vary widely but are mainly related to Heschel's published articles and books, speaking engagements, projects Heschel was working on, requests for copies of speeches and articles, visits to Israel and other locations, and a few commemorations after Heschel's death. A considerable amount of the correspondence is from notable individuals including Leo Baeck, David Ben Gurion, Martin Buber, Will Herberg, Mordecai Kaplan, Marshall Meyer, Thomas Merton, Reinhold Niebuhr, Jacob Neusner, Zalman Schachter-Shalomi, Gershom Sholem, Menachem M. Schneershon, Salman Schocken, Paul Tillich, Elie Wiesel, and Elemire Zolla. There are also many letters to Heschel from various students, admirers, detractors, and colleagues. Other materials in the series include clippings, programs, bulletins, telegrams, and handwritten notes. The materials are arranged chronologically.
  - [Letters and postcards], 1923-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Language(s): All materials in Hebrew and Yiddish.
    Contains correspondence, most of which with Yitzak Meir Levin.
  - Shazar, 1930, 1933, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Language(s): Most materials in Hebrew and Yiddish.
    Contains a variety of correspondence, among which are many letters by the Israeli President Zalman Shazar and letters related to the publication of Heschel's poems.
  - [Miscellaneous correspondence], 1930, 1950-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Language(s): Some materials in German, Hebrew and French.
    Correspondence from notable individuals including Leo Baeck, Arthur Goldberg, Will Herberg, George McGovern, Hermann Oberth, Chaim Potok, A. Philip Randolph, Lotte Jacobi, Arthur Rubenstein, Rabbi Menachem M. Schneerson, Karl Shapiro, Isaac Stern, Leopold Stokowski, Paul Tillich, Fritz Warburg, Leo Strauss, Elie Wiesel, and Simon Wiesenthal.
  - [Correspondence - Eduard Strauss], 1937-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Language(s): Most materials in German.
    Primarily correspondence from Eduard Strauss to Heschel. Also includes a corrected typescript of an essay, a newspaper clipping, and the monthly journal "Der Morgen" which includes and article by Strauss.
  - [Correspondence - Martin Buber], 1938-1962, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains letters and cards from Martin Buber to Heschel. Correspondence is sporadic, as such each year in the date range is not represented. Also include black and white photograph of Buber taken by Lotte Jacobi in the early 1930s. She sent the photograph to the Heschels in 1972.
  - [Letters and postcards], 1930s, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contains correspondence. The address of one letter is Heschel's brother Jacob.
  - [Correspondence], 1940, 1944-1957; 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Language(s): A few materials in Hebrew, Yiddish, and German.
    Mix of correspondence from friends, admirers and detractor, bulletins, programs, and clippings primarily related to Heschel's books and speaking engagements. Correspondents include Max Abbell, Will Herberg, Rabbi Samuel Dresner, and Siegfried Guggenheim. Also includes typed speech making reference to Heschel.
  - [Correspondence], 1940, 1944-1957; 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - JPS, 1940, 1946, 1948, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Language(s): A few materials in Hebrew.
    A mix of handwritten notes, clippings, programs and correspondence. Topics include faith, the ineffable, revelation and piety. Contains a number of letters related to Heschel's manuscript "Between God and Man" which became Man is Not Alone. Includes a program from the Opening of the 1940 Term at the Institute of Jewish Learning that Heschel directed in London.
  - [Correspondence - Alexander Altmann], 1940-1947, 1952, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Correspondence from Altmann to Heschel primarily written during World War II.
  - [Correspondence - Gershom Scholem], 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Language(s): All materials in Hebrew and Latin.
    Letters from Gershom Scholem to Heschel, with draft of one Heschel response. Includes detailed critiques and comments by Scholem of Heschel's work, as well as various requests for books and articles. Includes (unrelated?) note in Latin.
  - [Correspondence - Published Articles], 1941-1946; 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Language(s): Some materials in Hebrew, German, and Yiddish.
    Correspondence, postcards and clippings related to several of Heschel's published articles including "Zevi Diesendruck", "Analysis of Piety", "The Holy Dimension", "Faith", "Prayer", "The Quest for Certainty in Saadia's Philosophy", and an article on Maimonides.
  - [Correspondence - Published Articles], 1941-1946; 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - [Correspondence - Published Articles], 1941-1946; 3 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - [Correspondence], 1942-1943, 1953-1956; 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Language(s): A few materials in Hebrew, German, and French.
    A mix of correspondence, event programs, handwritten notes, and newspaper clipping on a variety of topics. Includes a letter from Jacob Neusner.
  - [Correspondence], 1942-1943, 1953-1956; 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - [Correspondence - Mordecai Kaplan], 1942-1945, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Correspondence primarily related to receipt and publication of Heschel's articles. Also includes a program for Kaplan's 70th birthday party.
  - Schocken, 1942-1949, 1952; 1 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Language(s): Some materials in German, Hebrew, and Yiddish.
    Primarily correspondence from Salman Schocken to Heschel which are both professional and personal in nature, including the publication of Heschel's essay "The Eastern European Era in Jewish History." Also includes correspondence from a variety of editors at Schocken Books, some handwritten notes, agendas, and an agreement between Heschel and Shocken Books.
  - Schocken, 1942-1949, 1952; 2 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Schocken, 1942-1949, 1952; 3 of 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - [Correspondence], 1943-1949, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Language(s): A few materials in Hebrew and Yiddish.
    Contains primarily letters, mostly of invitation for lectures and similar occasions. Also contains some brochures and newsletters, the clipping of the review of an anthology of Heschel's writings, and a letter of commendation of a book.
  - Personal, 1944-1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Language(s): Some materials in Yiddish and Hebrew.
    A mix of correspondence, event programs, synagogue bulletins and clippings.
  - [Miscellaneous], 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Language(s): Some materials in Yiddish.
    Contains a typescript of an essay about God and Man; letter to Heschel by Chayim Tzevi Cohen; letter to Heschel by Yiddish poet Celia Dropkin.
  - [Miscellaneous correspondence], 1947-1948, 1951, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Language(s): A few materials in Yiddish.
    Correspondence related to a variety of topics including the Diesendruck manuscript and a letter from Louis Finkelstein declining and invitation.
  - Ineffable, 1947-1957 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Language(s): Some materials in Hebrew and Yiddish.
    Mix of correspondence and clippings related to several of Heschel's published books. Includes a letter from Sylvia Heschel's father regarding his help with selling Heschel's books on the West Coast. Also includes a letter from Daniel Persky acknowledge receipt of books from Heschel and addressing their ideas and from R. Jacob Agus expressing thanks at two books Heschel sent him.
  - 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    A mix of correspondence and program booklets.
  - רבינוביץ, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Transliteration: Rabinovitz
    Translation: Rabinovitz
    Language(s): All materials in Yiddish.
    Numerous letters and notebooks from Aharon Rabinovitz (rare book dealer, Jaffa) to Heschel; letter from Rabbi Drubitcher of Tel Aviv to Heschel.
  - Letters, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Language(s): Some materials in Hebrew.
    A mix of handwritten notes, programs, and correspondence regarding speaking invitations and from Heschel's admirers, acquaintances and colleagues. Contains a galley proof of "Lest We Forget: A Ritual of Remembrance" by Rufus Learsi. Also includes a letter related to a reference letter that Heschel wrote for Marshall Meyer.
  - [Nachum Mordechai from Tchurtkov], 1951 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Contains some correspondence in Hebrew and Yiddish, as well as typescripts, concerning Nachum Mordechai from Tchurtkov.
  - Letters, 1951, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Language(s): A few materials in Hebrew and German.
    Correspondence from friends and admirers related to a variety of topics including invitations to speak or lecture, thank yous for visits, and requests for copies of articles. Correspondents include Julian Morgenstern, Roger Straus, Wolfe Kelman, and Caspar Nink.
  - Letters, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Language(s): Some materials in Hebrew, Yiddish, and Polish.
    A mix of correspondence and handwritten notes. Includes a copy of "Jewish Culture and Education in the Diaspora" by Hayim Greenberg.